Battle of Sekigahara

Conflict | Battle of Sekigahara
Part of | the Sekigahara Campaign↗ during the Sengoku period↗
Image | Sekigaharascreen.jpg
Edo-period↗ screen depicting the battle
Date | October 21, 1600
Place | Sekigahara↗ / Aonogahara Mino Province↗, present-day Gifu Prefecture↗, Japan
Territorial changes | Tokugawa clan↗ gains nominal control of all Japan
Result | Eastern army↗ victory
Combatant 1 | Western Army: Forces loyal to Ishida Mitsunari↗
Combatant 2 | Eastern Army: Forces loyal to Tokugawa Ieyasu↗
Commander 1 | Ishida Mitsunari↗
Commander 2 | Tokugawa Ieyasu↗: Overall commander
Strength 1 | 120,000 initially,
Strength 2 | 75,000 initially,
Casualties 1 | * Sekigahara Gunki Taisei: 8,000–32,000 killed
Casualties 2 | * Sekigahara Gunki Taisei: 4,000–10,000 killed

The Battle of Sekigahara (Shinjitai↗: 関ヶ原の戦い; Kyūjitai↗: 關ヶ原の戰い, Hepburn romanization↗: Sekigahara no Tatakai) was an important battle in Japan↗ which occurred on October 21, 1600 (Keichō↗ 5, 15th day of the 9th month) in what is now Gifu Prefecture↗, Japan, at the end of the Sengoku period↗.

This battle was fought by the forces of Tokugawa Ieyasu↗ against a coalition loyal to the Toyotomi clan, led by Ishida Mitsunari↗ on behalf of the young child Toyotomi Hideyori↗, from which several commanders defected before or during the battle, leading to a Tokugawa victory. The Battle of Sekigahara is often regarded as the most important battle in Japanese history.

Mitsunari's defeat in the Battle of Sekigahara is generally considered to be the beginning point of the Tokugawa shogunate↗, which ruled Japan for another two and a half centuries until 1868.

Background

The final years of Toyotomi Hideyoshi↗'s reign were turbulent. At the time of Hideyoshi's death, his heir, Toyotomi Hideyori↗, was only 5 years old, causing a power vacuum↗ in Japan.

Feuding factions

Main article: Sekigahara Campaign↗ In the years following the Imjin War↗ and the death of Hideyoshi, factional disputes arose between Ishida Mitsunari↗ and seven former Toyotomi generals including Katō Kiyomasa↗. After the subsequent death of Maeda Toshiie↗, a powerful and long-term ally of Hideyoshi and Oda Nobunaga↗, who had been sympathetic to Mitsunari's posturing, the uneasy balance of power began to dissolve. Tokugawa Ieyasu↗ gathered both Kiyomasa and Fukushima Masanori↗ to his cause in a bid to challenge the opposition from Mitsunari, who claimed to fight on behalf of the Toyotomi clan.

At this time, political tensions were high in the capital; In 1599, when the relationship between Ieyasu and Maeda Toshiie became strained and rumors of an attempted of conspiracy to storm the Tokugawa residence spread, Yoshitsugu accompanied Fukushima Masanori and other military commanders of the Toyotomi clan to the Tokugawa residence to guard Ieyasu. Later, when rumors of a plot to assassinate Ieyasu by Maeda Toshinaga↗ emerged, Yoshitsugu led an army to Echizen with the inner circle of Ishida Mitsunari, who had been ousted by Ieyasu. Maeda Toshinaga, who was accused of being involved in such conspiracies and contentiously but peacefully made to marry into the Tokugawa clan. Uesugi Kagekatsu↗, one of Hideyori's regents↗, stood against Ieyasu by building up his army, which Ieyasu officially questioned, demanding answers from Kyoto↗ about Kagekatsu's suspicious activity. Naoe Kanetsugu↗ responded with a mocking letter highlighting Ieyasu's own violations of Hideyoshi's orders.

Mitsunari met with Ōtani Yoshitsugu↗, Mashita Nagamori↗ and Ankokuji Ekei↗, conspiring to raise an anti-Tokugawa army, of which Mōri Terumoto↗ was appointed to be the overall commander. This coalition formed what came to be referred to as the Western Army. Terumoto immediately marched and captured Osaka Castle↗ while the main army of the Tokugawa were still on their way to suppress Kagekatsu.

At first, Mitsunari wanted to use Gifu Castle↗, which at that time was commanded by Oda Hidenobu↗ (the grandson of Nobunaga), and Ōgaki Castle↗ as choke points to impede the advances of the Eastern Army (the Tokugawa-led coalition). However, this plan was foiled by a number of campaign events:

Gifu Castle was captured↗ by the Eastern Army under Fukushima Masanori↗ and Ii Naomasa↗ before the main forces of the Western Army arrived.
On October 19, Shimazu Yoshihiro↗'s troops were beaten by Mizuno Katsunari↗ in a battle outside Sone Castle, and breaking through two or three baileys, after which Katsunari razed the outer moat of Ōgaki Castle and forced Yoshihiro to retreat into Ise Province↗.
Mitsunari realized that the Tokugawa army was heading towards Osaka Castle.

Following these failures and the threat against Osaka Castle, Mitsunari changed his plan and prepared his army for an open battle on the field of Sekigahara↗ against the main body of the Eastern Army, led by Ieyasu. As preparation for this inevitable conflict, Ieyasu had purchased massive quantities of Tanegashima matchlocks↗.

However, one day before the beginning of the battle, Kikkawa Hiroie↗, vassal of the Western Army-allied Mōri clan↗, colluded with the Eastern Army and promised that the Mōri clan would change sides during the battle, on the condition they would be pardoned after the war. Kuroda Yoshitaka↗ and Kuroda Nagamasa↗ served as representatives of the Eastern Army in this correspondence with Hiroie. Hiroie and his senior retainer Fukubara Hirotoshi↗ presented hostages to the Tokugawa side as proof for their cooperation with the latter.

Battle

See also: Japanese combat techniques↗ At dawn on October 21, 1600, the Tokugawa advance guard stumbled into Ishida's army; neither side saw each other because of dense fog caused by earlier rains. Both sides panicked and withdrew, but each was now aware of their adversary's presence and location. Mitsunari placed his position in defensive formation, while Ieyasu deployed his forces south of the Western Army position. Last-minute orders were issued and the battle began. Traditional opinion has stated the battle began around 08:00. However, recent Japanese historians' research estimates that the battle actually began closer to 10:00.

The battle started when Ii Naomasa↗, previously heavily involved in the Battle of Gifu Castle↗, commanded his famed unit of 3,600 crimson-clad Ii no Akazonae ("Ii's red devils") to attack the center of the Western Army. According to historian Watanabe Daimon, by many indications of the battle records, the assignment of Naomasa as ichiban-yari (the first unit to engage the enemy) suggests the armies may have already been settled before the battle. Fukushima Masanori concurred with Naomasa's intention to lead the first attack, as Naomasa was appointed by Ieyasu as the supreme field commander and was therefore responsible for all commands and strategies during the battle.

Naomasa charged forward with 30 spearmen and clashed with the ranks of the Western Army. Meanwhile, Fukushima Masanori↗ advanced from his position, following Naomasa and immediately engaging with troops led by Ukita Hideie↗.

At this point, the battle entered a deadlock. Ōta Gyūichi, who was present at the battle, wrote in his chronicle that "friends and foes are pushing each other" and "gunfire thunders while hails of arrows fly in the sky". According to records from Spanish accounts, 19 cannons from the De Liefde↗ [lt=De Liefde], a Dutch trading ship, were also used by the Tokugawa army in this battle as field artillery↗. Kani Saizō↗, the forerunner of Fukushima Masanori↗'s army, was recorded for taking the heads of 17 enemy combatants he killed during combat near Gifu Castle↗, and was noted by Ieyasu himself with praise after the battle concluded Famous swordsman Yagyū Munenori↗ also reported being participated on the side of Eastern Army, where he was later given 2,000 koku in Yamato Province↗ as recognition for his merit in this battle.

Western Army defectors

During the Battle of Sekigahara, several commanders of the Western Army changed sides, allying with the Tokugawa and changing the course of the battle. Perhaps the most notable of these defectors was Kobayakawa Hideaki↗, the nephew of Toyotomi Hideyoshi, whose disgruntlement with his uncle was exploited by the Tokugawa to sway his loyalty. Two prevailing theories exist regarding the timeline of Hideaki's defection:

The conventional theory regarding Hideaki's betrayal suggests that the defection occurred partway through the battle. Although he had agreed to defect to the Tokugawa side beforehand, Hideaki was allegedly hesitant during the battle and remained neutral, reportedly only joining the battle around noon as a member of the Eastern Army. Some later historical accounts claim that as the battle grew more intense, Ieyasu finally ordered his arquebuses to fire at Kobayakawa's position on Mt. Matsuo to force a choice. This version allegedly originated from an anecdote about Hideaki dating to the Edo period↗.
Modern Japanese researchers of Sekigahara, such as Jun Shiramine and Junji Mitsunari, have advanced the theory that Hideaki had already defected to the side of Tokugawa by the start of the battle, based on correspondence documents between Hideaki and Kuroda Nagamasa↗ before the battle, as well as Ōtani Yoshitsugu's army position at the start of the battle suggesting foreknowledge by the Western Army of Hideaki's betrayal. Historian Stephen Turnbull↗ also argues that the sheer distance between the Eastern Army positions and that of Kobayakawa, far out of range of arquebuses and likely too far for a shot to even be heard, makes the "story about Ieyasu ordering ‘cannon-shot’ into his ranks" to force Hideaki's hand very unlikely. Furthermore, Masayuki Fujimoto↗ argues the notion of Ieyasu' shooting cannot be corroborated by reliable historical sources of that time. Similarly, another historian, Yūichi Goza explains that the story of Ieyasu shooting at Hideaki's location comes from secondary sources from the Edo period, suggesting it may have been the result of dramatization and embellishment from pro-Tokugawa shogunate↗ historiography to aggrandize Ieyasu's success in Sekigahara. In fact, Goza explained that according to the theory of Jun Shiramine and other Japanese historian Takahashi Yōsuke, the reason why Mitsunari moved from Ogaki Castle to Sekigahara was not because they were enticed to confront the Eastern Army there, but because Mitsunari had learned Hideaki's betrayal even before the battle, and he wanted to rescue Otani Yoshitsugu, who was already arrived at Sekigahara.

Regardless of what actually transpired, the turncoat Kobayakawa forces overwhelmed Yoshitsugu's position, as according to Nakatomi Yūhan-ki (臣祐範記), "The armies of Kamigata↗ (referring to Western Army) had the upper hand, until Kobayakawa Hideaki betrayed them and attacked them from behind with over 15,000 men.". At the same time, Yoshitsugu's troops also engaged the units led by Tōdō Takatora↗, while subsequently Oda Nagamasu↗ and Honda Tadakatsu moved forward and intercepted the Toda Katsunari↗ units attacking Masanori's flank. This intercepting movement resulted in Katsunari's death in combat.

Following the defection of Hideaki, Western Army leaders Wakisaka Yasuharu↗, Ogawa Suketada↗, Akaza Naoyasu↗ and Kutsuki Mototsuna↗ also changed sides, further turning the battle in the Eastern Army's favor. These four commanders are recorded to have established contact and concluded deals with Tōdō Takatora↗, one of the main commanders of the Eastern Army, several days before the battle.

Mōri Terumoto↗, then daimyō of the Mōri clan↗, also defected from the Western Army during the battle by keeping his forces entrenched at Osaka Castle rather than joining the battle, then sending his vassal Kikkawa Hiroie↗ to quietly surrender to Ieyasu afterward. Professor Yoshiji Yamasaki of Toho University↗ states that any neutrality-for-territorial-preservation agreement was ineffective at best and badly backfired for the Mōri at worst, as their domains were greatly reduced by the Tokugawa following the battle, and some Mōri troops notably did fight with the Western Army at Sekigahara rather than maintaining their neutrality. Sentiments of defection were divided among the Mōri; Mōri Hidemoto↗, cousin of and commander under Terumoto, genuinely attempted to meet and aid the Western Army, though his efforts were sabotaged by Hiroie, who, under the pretense of being busy eating his meal, stationed his troops in front of Hidemoto, obstructing them from advancing and relieving Mitsunari. Hiroie also obstructed another Western Army contingent led by daimyō Chōsokabe Morichika↗ from marching and attacking the Tokugawa forces.

Collapse of the Western Army

One of the first and most notable weak points within the Western Army forces developed on Ukita Hideie's front. During the engagement, Hideie's forces began to wane and were steadily overcome by the forces of Fukushima Masanori due to the latter's superior troop quality. The disparity in combat effectiveness may have been attributable to the prior insurrection within the Ukita clan↗, which caused many senior samurai vassals of the Ukita to desert and join the Tokugawa faction. Hideie was thereby forced to enter Sekigahara with fresh recruits of rōnin↗ mercenaries to fill the gap left within his army. This proved fatal over the course of long-term combat against the Fukushima clan's more disciplined and trained regular troops; the Ukita clan ranks began to break and finally collapse under pressure despite outnumbering the Fukushima.

To the south, Ōtani Yoshitsugu was outnumbered in a successful attack led by Kobayakawa Hideaki; Hiratsuka Tamehiro, along with Oda Nobunaga's sons, Oda Nobuyoshi and Oda Nagatsugu, led a 360-man vanguard on the Fujikawa Plateau under Yoshitsugu. He fought back against Hideaki's troops for a while. However, he was unable to withstand against simultaneous attacks by the forces of Wakisaka Yasuharu↗, Tōdō Takatora↗ and Kyōgoku Takatomo↗. In the end, Tamehiro was killed by either Kashii Taibei, a vassal of Yamauchi Kazutoyo↗, or by Yokota Kohansuke, a vassal of Hideaki. Yoshitsugu committed suicide and his troops retreated shortly thereafter. Amidst the confusion within the Otani clan troops, Toda Katsushige↗ was slain by the Tokugawa forces. The Ōtani forces' rout left the Western Army's right flank wide open, which Masanori and Hideaki then exploited to roll the flank of the Western Army. Mitsunari, realizing the situation was desperate, began to retreat his troops. Meanwhile, Western Army commander Shima Sakon↗ was engaged by the troops of Kuroda Nagamasa↗, who had taken a detour on the north to flank the Mitsunari and Sakon positions. In the end, Sakon was shot and fatally wounded by a round from an arquebus.

Following the capitulation of Sakon's unit, Shimazu Yoshihiro↗ found his troops completely surrounded by Masanori and Honda Tadakatsu↗ from the front, while Hideaki troops attacked his rear. The Shimazu troops only managed to break their encirclement after devastating casualties, escaping with only 200 soldiers remaining; even then, they were pursued by Ii Naomasa until the latter was incapacitated by a shot from a rifleman.

The forces of the Western Army continued to crumble without the arrival of reinforcements, their situation continued to deteriorate due to the waves of defections, until the battle had finally concluded. Historian Andō Yūichirō estimated that the battle in Sekigahara took place in its entirety over a mere two hours – from 10:00 to 12:00 – contrary to the Edo-period accepted theory of the battle lasting twice as long. The two hours duration was found in the primary source of the letter of Ieyasu himself which dated October 21, 1600 (Keichō 5, 15th day of the 9th month), at the day of the battle, for Date Masamune↗, informing the latter about the timing of Eastern Army victory at Sekigahara.

Late arrivals

The combined Eastern Army forces of Tokugawa Hidetada↗ and Sakakibara Yasumasa↗, who commanded as many as 38,000 soldiers, were at the time of the battle bogged down in the Siege of Ueda↗ against Sanada Masayuki↗. At the same time, 15,000 Western Army soldiers were being held up by 500 troops under Hosokawa Yūsai↗ in the Siege of Tanabe↗ in Maizuru↗, many of the former refusing to advance out of their respect for the Hosokawa↗. Due to these incidents, large proportions of both armies' forces ultimately never participated in the clash at Sekigahara.

Another Western Army contingent that failed to reach the Sekigahara battlefield was led by Tachibana Muneshige↗, who had been stalled by Kyōgoku Takatsugu↗ in the Siege of Ōtsu↗. As result, Muneshige was forced to remain at Osaka Castle after learning of the Western Army's annihilation at Sekigahara. However, when Mōri Terumoto (also at Osaka Castle) offered his surrender to the Eastern Army, Muneshige departed with his army and returned to his homeland in Kyushu↗.

Aftermath

Although the Eastern Army was victorious, the soldiers of Mōri who did not participate in the battle and holed in the Osaka Castle were largely intact. Ieyasu feared that Terumoto would continue to resist by barricading himself in Osaka Castle with Hideyori. Therefore, on September 17, Ieyasu sent a letter to Terumoto to convince him to leave Osaka Castle by promise of a peaceful settlement between the two.

As soon as the news of the Eastern Army's victory at Sekigahara reached Ogaki Castle, which at the time was still besieged by Mizuno Katsunari, Western Army-affiliated garrison commander Akizuki Tanenaga↗ immediately surrendered and opened the castle for Katsunari. In response, Katsunari immediately wrote to Ii Naomasa asking that Ieyasu pardon Tanenaga, which Ieyasu accepted.

The most prominent political effect of the Eastern Army victory in Sekigahara was the shifting authority to assign military ranks↗ and redistribute lands from the Toyotomi clan to Tokugawa Ieyasu. Immediately following the battle, Ieyasu redistributed domains worth 6.8 million koku↗, primarily as recompense for the allies instrumental in his victory:

Ikeda Terumasa↗ was reassigned from Mikawa Province↗, Yoshida region to a 520,000-koku domain↗ in Harima Province↗, Himeji↗ region.
Tōdō Takatora↗ was reassigned to a 200,000-koku domain in Imabari, Ehime↗.
Matsudaira Tadayoshi↗ was reassigned from a 100,000-koku domain in Musashi Province↗, Yuki region, to a 520,000-koku domain in Echizen Province↗, Fukui↗ region.
Yūki Hideyasu↗ was reassigned from a 101,000-koku domain in Shimōsa Province↗, Shinobu region, to a 569,000-koku domain in Owari Province↗, Kiyosu↗ region.
Gamō Hideyuki↗ was reassigned from a 180,000-koku domain in Shimotsuke Province↗, Utsunomiya↗ region, to a 600,000-koku domain in Mutsu Province↗, Aizu↗ region.
Maeda Toshinaga↗ had his 835,000-koku domain in Kaga Province↗, Kanazawa↗ region, expanded to 1,100,000 koku.
Katō Kiyomasa↗ had his 195,000-koku domain in Higo Province↗, Kumamoto↗ region, expanded to 515,000 koku.
Kuroda Nagamasa was reassigned from a 180,000-koku domain in Buzen Province↗, Nakatsu↗ region, to a 523,000-koku domain in Chikuzen Province↗, Fukuoka↗ region.
Fukushima Masanori had his 200,000-koku domain in the area of contemporary Aki District, Hiroshima↗, expanded to 498,000 koku.
Horio Tadauji↗ had his domains in Matsue, Izumo, expanded to 240,000 koku.
Asano Yoshinaga↗ was assigned to 376,560-koku domain and the control of Wakayama Castle in Kii Province.
Ieyasu also bestowed increases of at least into 10,000 koku to many of his fudai daimyō↗ (Tokugawa clan hereditary vassals) whose domain were less than 10,000 koku before the battle.

Notably, Kobayakawa Hideaki, whose defection from the Western Army contributed greatly to Ieyasu's victory, was bestowed a domain which covered parts of Bizen Province↗ and Mimasaka Province↗ and which was worth 520,000 koku. This redistribution of domains was done verbally, instead of by formal letter of intent↗. Historian Watanabe Daimon suspected this was because Ieyasu was still wary of the existence of Toyotomi clan which had been inherited by Toyotomi Hideyori.

Another defecting daimyo who awarded by Ieyasu was Kikkawa Hiroie. Ieyasu gave him the land which belonged to Mōri Terumoto for his service in obstructing the Western Army during the battle, rewarding Hiroie by punishing Terumoto. This meant Ieyasu reneged his earlier promise to give pardon to Terumoto, and as the Kikkawa clan↗ was traditional vassal of the Mōri clan, Hiroie refused the bestowal and asked Ieyasu to not punish the Mōri clan. Ieyasu cited the reason of his decision to neglect his promise to Terumoto as various letters from many Western Army collaborators which, seized after the battle, heavily implied Terumoto's major role in anti-Tokugawa movement during the war. On October 3, Hiroie once again petitioned to Ieyasu to spare Terumoto from abolishment, and for the provinces of Suo and Nagato Domains bestowed to him to be given to Terumoto. On October 10, Ieyasu decided to spare the Mōri clan from territorial abolition, but he still stripped away much of Terumoto's fiefs, from eight provinces to only two provinces in Suo and Nagato with a total stipend of 298,000 koku.

Takenaka Shigekado↗, who was awarded with 1,000 koku after the battle, was immediately ordered by Ieyasu to build Kubizuka↗ (head-burial mound) for those who had fallen in the battle of Sekigahara. After that, Shigekado did not accompany the main force of the Eastern Army, which headed west. In the meantime, he captured Konishi Yukinaga, who had fled to Mount Ibuki, and delivered him to Ieyasu, who was advancing to Kusatsu in Omi. As appreciation, Ieyasu then bestowed upon him the sword that belonged to Yukinaga.

Ieyasu bestowed smaller domain increases to the three remaining Shitennō↗ (Ii Naomasa, Honda Tadakatsu, and Sakakibara Yasumasa↗), his closest high-ranking generals, as compared to those he offered to newer commanders and vassals. Some 20th-21st historians believed it is possible this perceived disparity was the result of those generals choosing to decline Ieyasu's offers of extensive compensation. However, although Yasumasa indeed declined Ieyasu's offer for 250,000 koku of Mito Domain↗, Arthur Lindsay Sadler↗ recorded that Naomasa and Honda Tadakatsu expressed dissatisfaction due to their rewards from Ieyasu.

Kinoshita Katsutoshi↗ became one of the two Eastern Army daimyo who was stripped from his domain despite siding with Ieyasu during the conflict. The perceived reason was because of his cowardice as he abandoned Fushimi castle during its siege, leaving Torii Mototada↗ to defend the castle alone. This enraged Ieyasu, who demoted him. However, after his father, Iesada, died in 1608, through the intermediation of Kōdai-in↗, he was granted his estate (25,000 koku in Ashimori Domain↗, at Bitchu Province↗) and was left to his discretion. Ieyasu had also decided to divide his estate between Katsutoshi and Toshifusa, but Kodaiin gave the entire estate to Katsutoshi as she favored him. Another Daimyo was Miyabe Nagafusa↗, who was demoted and stripped from his title, due to slander by Tanaka Yoshimasa↗ that Nagafusa intended to defect to the Western Army, despite participating in the attack on Sawayama Castle as part of the Eastern Army.

As for the generals of the defeated Western Army, roughly 87 daimyō had their domains confiscated and their power stripped due to their support of Mitsunari in the battle. The long-standing Chōsokabe clan↗, headed by Chōsokabe Morichika↗, was stripped of its title and domain of Tosa Province↗, which was consequently given to Yamauchi Kazutoyo↗ in recognition of his service to the Tokugawa. Several former Chōsokabe retainers resisted↗ the forcible takeover by the Tokugawa and Kazutoyo; in response, Ii Naomasa sent military reinforcements to assist Kazutoyo in suppressing the rebellion of Chōsokabe vassals in Tosa. Suzuki Hyōe, vassal of Naomasa, relieved Kazutoyo with an army transported by 8 ships, ultimately pacifying the region in 5 weeks after killing about 273 enemies.

On September 17, Ieyasu dispatched his army, led by Kobayakawa Hideaki, to attack Sawayama Castle↗ in Ōmi Province↗, the home base of Mitsunari. Most of the castle's troops had been sent to Sekigahara, leaving the castle's garrison with only 2,800 men. Despite Mitsunari's absence, the defense of the castle was initially successful under the leadership of Mitsunari's father Ishida Masatsugu↗ and brother Masazumi. Following the defection of retainer Moritomo Hasegawa and other defenders, the castle was opened to the besieging army; most of Mitsunari's relatives, including Masatsugu, Masazumi, and Mitsunari's wife Kagetsuin, were killed in battle or committed suicide.

In response to Shimazu Yoshihiro↗'s support of the Western Army, Ieyasu prepared a massive punitive expedition to Kyushu, to be led by his son Tokugawa Hidetada↗. This force was to be composed of Eastern Army forces thereupon engaged in the West, including the armies of Katō Kiyomasa↗, Kuroda Yoshitaka↗, Nabeshima Naoshige↗, and the Tachibana clan↗. However, this operation was aborted once Shimazu Yoshihisa↗, the head of the Shimazu clan↗, entered negotiations with Ieyasu. Shimazu-Tokugawa deliberations continued until 1602 and were aided by the intercession of Kiyomasa, Yoshitaka, and Tachibana Muneshige↗; ultimately, the Shimazu clan avoided punishment, becoming the only Western Army-aligned clan to avoid losing territory after the defeat at Sekigahara.

On November 6, Ishida Mitsunari, Konishi Yukinaga↗ and Ankokuji Ekei↗ were captured and executed.

In 1603, Ieyasu was officially appointed as shōgun↗ by Emperor↗ Go-Yōzei↗.

In 1931, the location of the battle was registered as a Monument of Japan↗. The positions of Ieyasu and Mitsunari's armies, and that of the death of Ōtani Yoshitsugu, are commemorated therein.

Historical Analysis

As the conclusion of the Battle of Sekigahara has served as the de facto beginning of the Edo period, and more generally, of the return of stability to Japan, in 1664, Hayashi Gahō↗, Tokugawa historian and rector of Yushima Seidō↗, wrote:

Evil-doers and bandits were vanquished and the entire realm submitted to Lord Ieyasu, praising the establishment of peace and extolling his martial virtue. That this glorious era that he founded may continue for ten thousands upon ten thousands of generations, coeval with heaven and earth.

Jakob Meckel↗, (28 March 1842 – 5 July 1906), a general in the Prussian army↗ and foreign advisor to the government of Meiji period↗ Japan, once analyzed the map of the forces distribution at the Battle of Sekigahara. Jakob deduced that the Western Army, due to greater numbers and better positions on higher ground, should have won. At first, Jakob was skeptical with a Japanese staff officer's explanation that it was the Eastern army had won, only believing so after the officer explained to him about the flow of the battle.

20th-21st century Japanese historians such as Kasaya Kazuhiko, Mizuno Goki, Watanabe Daimon↗ and others pointed that among major factors which influenced the result of the battle of Sekigahara, it was the perceived unpopularity of Ishida Mitsunari and the resentment of many powerful daimyo lords of that time, particularly those who involved in the Japanese invasions of Korea↗, as they felt their achievements during the campaign was undermined by Mitsunari's report, or even Mitsunari's own mismanagement under Hideyoshi.

One notable example was in 1598, when several daimyo lords, which colloquially known as the "Military Faction" of Toyotomi government, such as Fukushima Masanori, Katō Kiyomasa, Ikeda Terumasa, Hosokawa Tadaoki, Asano Yoshinaga, Katō Yoshiaki, Kuroda Nagamasa, Hachisuka Iemasa↗, Tōdō Takatora, and Kuroda Yoshitaka↗ brought their troops and entourage to storm Ishida's residence to confront Mitsunari↗. At first, those daimyo lords gathered at Kiyomasa's mansion in Osaka Castle↗, and from there they marched to Mitsunari's mansion. However, Mitsunari had learned of this from a report by a servant of Toyotomi Hideyori↗ named Jiemon Kuwajima, and fled to mansion together with Shima Sakon↗ and others to hide. The heated situation forced Mitsunari to even flee and hid himself at the Satake Yoshinobu↗'s residence, and then at Fushimi Castle↗, Before Tokugawa Ieyasu himself act as mediator of the dispute to calm those daimyo who resented Mitsunari.

Even Kobayakawa Hideaki's fief of Chikuzen↗ and Chikugo↗ was confiscated due to the rumored Mitsunari's slander against him on the aftermath of Korean war. It was said that Hideaki held grudge towards Mitsunari as he thought the confiscation of his fief was because Mitsunari game him bad assessment During the siege of Ulsan↗. However, Watanabe Daimon warned that such rumor was baseless as Hideaku was not involved in the siege of Ulsan, and the rumor of Mitsunari influenced the confiscation of Hideaki's domains was probably just because the political mood and historical bias during that time, where many tends to blame Mitsunari for everything goes wrong prior to Sekigahara battle. Nevertheless, Daimon still pointed out that Mitsunari already made too many enemies the moment he started hostility against Ieyasu, as according to the Keicho Kenbunsho, on the eve of the battle of Sekigahara, even his close ally Otani Yoshitsugu↗ warned Mitsunari, saying, "You are hated by the daimyos, so if you raise an army, those who sued you last year will become your enemies.". Furthermore, Yoshitsugu also cited the difference in the amount of Koku↗, the number of soldiers, and the amount of material resources between Ieyasu and Mitsunari, as well as the difference in military experience and ability, and said that there was no way Mitsunari could defeat Ieyasu.

Yūichi Goza, Assistant Professor at the International Research Center for Japanese Studies↗, concludes that Mitsunari naively overestimated the authority of Toyotomi clan, while in reality, many daimyo were pragmatic enough to prioritize following Tokugawa Ieyasu, who was viewed as extremely powerful figure of the time. Goza pointed out several indications one of them is the surprising letter of Mitsunari with the indication he believes he still could persuade Fukushima Masanori to join him to oppose Ieyasu. Similarly, Toshi Kohara↗, a Japanese anthropologist and professor emeritus of Rikkyo University↗, believed that despite those daimyo were originally vassals of Hideyoshi, they are convinced that fighting for Ieyasu and opposing Mitsunari was the best course for the interest of Hideyoshi's heir, Toyotomi Hideyori↗.

Kazuto Hongo↗, researcher from the University of Tokyo↗, remarked that Sekigahara campaign↗ was essentially more of Ieyasu's political victory rather than military one. This took account from most political and factional advantages Ieyasu has secured that ultimately become critical factors for the outcome of this war, including the approval from the mother of Hideyori, Ōmandokoro↗, for his operation.

According to one historical record from Chikugo Province↗, Tschibana Muneshige was once advised by his senior retainer, Komono Masutoki, to side with the Eastern Army, saying that the Western Army had no chance of winning. However, Muneshige replied that he does not care about winning or losing.

Statistics and chronology

+ Commanders
Commanders of Eastern Army (Tokugawa Force) | Commanders of Western Army (Ishida Force)
*Tokugawa Ieyasu↗ (head of the alliance): 30,000 men | *Mōri Terumoto↗ (official head of the alliance) (not present)

The participants of the Battle of Sekigahara are listed below, with corresponding troop count estimates (in tens of thousands): ○ = Main daimyō who participated in the Battle of Sekigahara

● = Daimyō who defected

| Daimyō | Kokudaka (hundreds) | | Daimyō | Kokudaka (hundreds)
Western Army | Mōri Terumoto↗ | 121.0 | Eastern Army | Tokugawa Ieyasu↗ ○ | 256.0
Uesugi Kagekatsu↗ | 120.0 | Maeda Toshinaga↗ | 84.0
Satake Yoshinobu↗ | 54.0 | Date Masamune↗ | 58.0
Shimazu Yoshihiro↗ ○ | 73.0 | Katō Kiyomasa↗ | 20.0
Ukita Hideie↗ ○ | 57.0 | Fukushima Masanori↗ ○ | 24.0
Ishida Mitsunari↗ ○ | 19.4 | Hosokawa Tadaoki↗ ○ | 18.0
Konishi Yukinaga↗ ○ | 20.0 | Asano Yoshinaga↗ ○ | 16.0
Mashita Nagamori↗ | 20.0 | Ikeda Terumasa↗ ○ | 15.0
Ogawa Suketada↗ ● | 7.0 | Kuroda Nagamasa↗ ○ | 18.0
Ōtani Yoshitsugu↗ ○ | 5.0 | Katō Yoshiaki↗ ○ | 10.0
Wakisaka Yasuharu↗ ● | 3.0 | Tanaka Yoshimasa ○ | 10.0
Ankokuji Ekei↗ ○ | 6.0 | Tōdō Takatora↗ ○ | 11.0
Kobayakawa Hideaki↗ ● | 37.0 | Mogami Yoshiaki↗ | 24.0
Oda Hidenobu↗ | 13.5 | Yamauchi Kazutoyo↗ ○ | 6.0
Chōsokabe Morichika↗ ○ | 22.0 | Hachisuka Yoshishige↗ | 17.7
Kutsuki Mototsuna↗ ● | 2.0 | Honda Tadakatsu↗ ○ | (10.0)
Akaza Naoyasu↗ ● | 2.0 | Terazawa Hirotaka↗ ○ | 8.0
Kikkawa Hiroie↗ ● | (14.2) | Ikoma Kazumasa↗ ○ | 15.0
Natsuka Masaie↗ ○ | 5.0 | Ii Naomasa↗ ○ | (12.0)
Mōri Hidemoto↗ ○ | (20.0) | Matsudaira Tadayoshi↗ ○ | 13.0
Toda Katsushige↗ ○ | 1.0 | Tsutsui Sadatsugu↗ ○ | 20.0
Sanada Masayuki↗ | 4.0 | Kyōgoku Takatomo↗ ○ | 10.0

Below is a chronology of the events leading up to and shortly following the Battle of Sekigahara:

May 7 – Ieyasu asks Uesugi Kagekatsu↗ for explanations for his military mobilization. Kagekatsu refuses Ieyasu.
June 8 – Ieyasu calls his allies to punish the Uesugi↗.
July 12 – Ieyasu holds a meeting in Osaka↗ to plan the punishment of the Uesugi, attended by Hosokawa Tadaoki↗, Date Masamune↗, Mogami Yoshiaki↗, Satake Yoshinobu↗ and Nanbu Toshinao↗.
July 26 – Ieyasu leaves Fushimi Castle↗ after meeting with Torii Mototada↗.
August 16 – Mitsunari meets with Ōtani Yoshitsugu↗ and convinces him to take sides against the Tokugawa.
August 17 – Ishida Mitsunari↗, Ankokuji Ekei↗, Ōtani Yoshitsugu↗ and Mashita Nagamori↗ meet in Sawayama↗ and agree to ask Mōri Terumoto↗ to become commander in chief of the alliance. Nagamori secretly sends Ieyasu news about the meeting.
August 19 – Siege of Tanabe↗: while Hosokawa Tadaoki↗'s army was en route to attack Uesugi and Mitsunari's Western Army, Ikoma Chikamasa↗'s forces under Onoki Shigekatsu attack Tanabe Castle against Hosokawa Fujitaka↗.
August 22 – Mōri Terumoto arrives at Osaka Castle↗ and takes command of the Western Army.
August 23 – Battle of Gifu Castle↗: Western-aligned Oda Hidenobu↗ is besieged and defeated by Ikeda Terumasa↗, Ikeda Sen↗ and Fukushima Masanori↗ of the Eastern Army.
August 27 – Siege of Fushimi↗, led by Mitsunari and Kobayakawa Hideaki↗.
August 29 – Ieyasu establishes his headquarters in Oyama, Shizuoka↗ to discuss strategy with allies.
August 30 – Battle of Asai↗: Maeda Toshinaga↗ of the Eastern Army holds back the forces of Niwa Nagashige↗ and Uesugi Kagekatsu↗.
September 1 – Siege of Shiroishi↗: Uesugi Kagekatsu loses Shiroishi Castle to Date Masamune↗'s pro-Tokugawa troops.
September 6 – Fall of Tanabe Castle↗ to the Western Army. Fujitaka enters Kameyama Castle↗, governed by Maeda Shigekatsu↗ in Tanba↗.
September 7 – Tokugawa ally Maeda Toshinaga↗ attacks his brother, Toshimasa↗, and besieges Daishoji Castle↗. The commander of the garrison, Yamaguchi Munenaga↗, commits seppuku↗.
September 8 – Fall of Fushimi Castle↗: Torii Mototada↗ and Matsudaira Ietada↗ die.
September 10 – Ieyasu returns to Edo Castle↗ from Oyama.
September 15 – Mitsunari's Western army arrives at Ogaki Castle↗.
September 29 – Nabeshima Naoshige↗ and other Western Army generals besiege Matsuoka Castle↗. The Eastern Army occupies the heights of Akasaka, near Ogaki Castle↗.
September 29 – Fall of Gifu Castle↗ to the Eastern Army. Tokugawa Hidetada↗ heads towards Nakasendo↗.
September 30 – Mōri Hidemoto↗ lays siege to Anotsu Castle↗, held by Tomita Nobutaka.
October 1 – Mitsunari returns to Sawayama Castle↗ from Ogaki, asking Terumoto to march. Terumoto has been at Osaka Castle defending Toyotomi Hideyori↗.
October 7 – Ieyasu leaves Edo with 30,000 men heading towards Tokaido↗.
October 9 – Tokugawa Hidetada↗ reaches Komoro, Nagano↗, and against the orders of his father, diverts his forces towards Ueda↗.
October 12 – Ieyasu passes through Shimada in Suruga↗. Hidetada camps in Sometani village to besiege Ueda Castle↗, held by Sanada Masayuki↗.
October 13 – Ieyasu passes through Nakaizumi in Tōtōmi↗. Mōri Hidemoto↗ and Kikkawa Hiroie↗ enter Mino↗ and set up camp near Mount Nangu↗. Western Army commanders Mōri Hidekane↗, Tachibana Muneshige↗ and Tsukushi Hirokado↗ besiege Ōtsu Castle↗, held by Kyōgoku Takatsugu↗.
October 14 – Ieyasu receives a secret messenger from Kobayakawa Hideaki↗, who offers him support. Naoe Kanetsugu↗ leads the Uesugi forces against Mogami Yoshiaki↗ at the Siege of Hasedo↗.
October 16 – Hidetada abandons the Siege of Ueda↗ Castle and heads to Mino.
October 19 – Ieyasu arrives at Gifu Castle in Mino. Kuroda Yoshitaka↗ defeats Ōtomo Yoshimune↗ and other Ishida-allied generals at the Battle of Ishigakibara↗.
October 20 – Ieyasu moves to Akasaka↗. The two coalitions make contact at Kuisegawa↗, near Akasaka. The Eastern force retreats to Sekigahara↗. The Western coalition heads to Sekigahara from Ogaki Castle.
October 21 – Battle of Sekigahara
October – Siege of Yanagawa↗: the last battle of the Kyūshū Sekigahara Campaign.
October 30 – Date Masamune↗ tries to conquer Fukushima Castle↗ but fails and retreats. (In May 1601, during the Battle of Matsukawa↗, Masamune is repelled by Honjō Shigenaga↗.)
November 5 – Naoe Kanetsugu↗ calls for a full withdrawal of all Uesugi forces, putting an end to Uesugi's campaigns in the north.

Cultural depictions

Owing to its pivotal status as the climax of the Sengoku period, the Battle of Sekigahara is a common subject of modern depictions and retellings:

In 1966, Ryōtarō Shiba↗ authored the historical novel Sekigahara, which has since been adapted into a 2017 film of the same name↗ directed by Masato Harada.
James Clavell↗ included a historical-fiction depiction of the battle in his 1975 novel Shōgun↗, later adapted for television in the United States as a miniseries in 1980↗ and again as a series in 2024↗.
Tokyo Broadcasting System↗ aired a television miniseries↗ about the battle in January 1981, also entitled Sekigahara↗ [lt=Sekigahara].
The 2000 real-time tactics video game Kessen↗ is set during the conflict between the Tokugawa and Toyotomi clans, and features the Battle of Sekigahara.
The 2011 grand strategy video game Total War: Shogun 2↗ includes Sekigahara as a historical battle, in which the player controls Mitsunari's Western Army.
The 2017 action RPG video game Nioh↗ portrays events related to the battle.
Manga series “Vagabond” portrays legendary samurai Miyamoto Musashi as a participant in the battle.
The battle was featured in 2023 historical drama What Will You Do, Ieyasu?↗
While this battle has been portrayed in numerous NHK Taiga dramas, the version in the 2000 production "Aoi↗"—aired to coincide with the 400th anniversary of the Battle of Sekigahara—is particularly notable. The production utilized 60 horses to film the combat sequences. Actor Masahiko Tsugawa↗, who played the lead role, praised the result as "a magnificent battle scene that will remain in the history of Japanese television drama.
The battle of Sekigahara is mentioned in the movie Exhuma (2024) by a resurrected japanese general.

Notes

References

"関ケ原 戦いの場所は「青野カ原」 合戦直後の文書に記載"↗. 毎日新聞. The Mainichi Newspapers. 2016
"関ヶ原合戦で東軍を勝利に導いた井伊直政は、本当に抜け駆けをしたのか"↗. yahoo.co.jp/expert/articles/. 渡邊大門 無断転載を禁じます。 © LY Corporation. 2023
Jun Shiramine. 関ヶ原合戦の真実―脚色された天下分け目の戦い―. 宮帯出版社, 2014. p. 160–161
『関原軍記大成』
"【どうする家康 予習】関ヶ原合戦…江戸幕府の公式記録『徳川実紀』が伝える当日の様子を紹介:2ページ目"↗. mag.japaaan.com. Japaaan Magazine. 2023. p. 1–2
"Choyakyubun Hokou: A compilation of historical materials relating to the founding history of the Tokugawa clan"↗. National Archives of Japan
『関原合戦記』
"Battle of Sekigahara | Summary, Facts, & Outcome | Britannica"↗. www.britannica.com
Masaki Kokuhata↗, "秀吉死後の政局と大谷吉継の豊臣政権復帰". 日本歴史. 2012, no. 772 September
図解関ヶ原合戦までの90日: 勝敗はすでに決まっていた!. PHP研究所, 2013. p. 53. ISBN 978-4569815541
尾西市史 通史編 · Volume 1. 尾西市役所, 1998. p. 242
参謀本部. 石川貞清三成ノ陣ニ赴ク. 日本戦史. 関原役. 元真社, 1911
新訂寛政重修諸家譜 6. 八木書店, 1964. ISBN 978-4-7971-0210-9
関ヶ原合戦史料集. 藤井治左衛門, 1979. p. 421
戦国時代の謎と怪異. 日本文芸社, 1977. p. 191
大垣藩戶田家の見聞書 二百年間集積史料「御家耳袋」. 愛文書林, 2006. p. 32. ISBN 4872940520
Sokō Yamaga↗. 新編武家事紀. 新人物往來社, 1969. p. 370, 613, 1044
岐阜県史 Volume 6. 巌南堂書店, 1965
大重平六覚書
"関ヶ原合戦の前日、毛利輝元は本領安堵を条件として、徳川家康と和睦していた"↗. yahoo.co.jp/expert/articles/. 渡邊大門 無断転載を禁じます。 © LY Corporation. 2023
"関ヶ原合戦と小早川秀秋…近年の研究動向を踏まえ、裏切りの真相にアプローチ！"↗. Sengoku-his. sengoku-his.com. 2023
"だから織田と豊臣はあっさり潰れた…徳川家康が｢戦国最後の天下人｣になれた本当の理由"↗. President Online. President Inc. 2022. p. 1–5
"「島津豊久」は父・家久と伯父・義弘の薫陶を受けた名将であった！"↗. 戦国ヒストリー. sengoku-his.com. 2024 References from: * Kirino Sakujin (関ヶ原島津退き口―敵中突破三〇〇里― / Shimazu's Retreat at Sekigahara: Breaking Through Enemy Lines 300 Miles (Gakken Publishing, 2010) * Niina Kazuhito(薩摩島津氏 / Satsuma Shimazu Clan) (Ebisu Kosho Publishing, 2014) * Niina Kazuhito (島津家久・豊久父子と日向国 / Shimazu Iehisa and Toyohisa, Father and Son, and Hyuga Province ) (Miyazaki Prefecture, 2017) * Niina Kazuhito (「不屈の両殿」島津義久・義弘 関ヶ原後も生き抜いた才智と武勇 / Shimazu Yoshihisa and Yoshihiro: The "Indomitable Princes" – The Wisdom and Bravery that Survived After Sekigahara ) (Kadokawa、2021年)
Turnbull & Rava (2012, p. 48)
Bryant (1995)
James Murdoch↗. A history of Japan. London; New York: Routledge, 1996. p. 417. ISBN 978-0-415-15076-7
Kazuhiko Kasaya (笠谷和比古). 関ヶ原合戦と近世の国制. 思文閣出版社, 2000. p. 69–73
The Spirit of Samurai. Mega Press Nusantara, 31 August 2023. p. 78. ISBN 9786238313402
Mike Hanagan and Pat Cox. Legends of Kent. Pat Cox / Mike Hanagan, 2012. p. 61. ISBN 978-1-4701-7424-8
Cannon use during the winter siege of Osaka.
楠戸 義昭. 戦国武将名言録 (PHP文庫). PHP研究所, 2006. p. 375. ISBN 4-569-66651-5
Imamura Yoshio, ed. 史料 柳生新陰流. 新人物往来社 / 人物往来社, 1967. p. 66
Stephen Turnbull. "The battle of Sekigahara – what went right?"↗. Osprey Publishing. 28 August 2019
Masayuki Fujimoto. "関ヶ原合戦で家康は小早川軍に鉄砲を撃ち込ませてはいない". 歴史読本. 1984, no. 特別増刊
"家康は｢早く裏切れ｣と小早川秀秋に催促したわけではない…関ヶ原合戦の｢家康神話｣が崩壊する衝撃的新説"↗. President Online（プレジデントオンライン）. President Inc.. 2023. p. 1–4
Yuichi Goza↗, "大河ドラマ『どうする家康』解説⑧：小早川秀秋は事前に裏切っていたか？"↗. アゴラ 言論プラットフォーム. 2023-11-29
Jun Shiramine. "在京公家・僧侶などの日記における関ヶ原の戦い関係等の記載について(その1)". 時系列データベース化の試み(慶長5年3月~同年12月). February 2016, no. 57, pp. 113–123
Jun Shiramine. "藤堂高虎は関ヶ原で大谷吉継と戦った―『藤堂家覚書』の記載検討を中心に―". 十六世紀史論叢. 2018, no. 9号
Takayanagi Mitsutoshi. 戦国人名辞典. 吉川弘文館, 1981. p. 163–164 quoting: 慶長見聞書
Fujita Tatsuo. 藤堂高虎論 -初期藩政史の研究. 塙書房, 2018. ISBN 978-4827312966
"関ヶ原合戦の前日、すでに毛利輝元は徳川家康と和睦していた！？"↗. rekishikaido. PHPオンライン. p. 1–3
Shiramine Jun「Considerations on the battle formation diagrams of the Battle of Sekigahara」(Beppu University↗ Graduate School Bulletin, No. 15, 2013)
"福島正則は関ヶ原本戦で宇喜多秀家を打ち破り、東軍を勝利に導いた"↗. yahoo.co.jp/expert/articles/. 渡邊大門 無断転載を禁じます。 © LY Corporation. 2023
豊臣期の宇喜多氏と宇喜多秀家. 岩田書院, 2010. p. 99. ISBN 9784872946123
Ikeda Koichi, ed. 大谷刑部のすべて. 新人物往来社, 2000. p. 261
Historiographical Institute, University of Tokyo↗, ed., 大日本史料 第１２編之５. 東京大学, 1904. p. 252
Pitelka (2016, pp. 118–142)
関ケ原合戦前後: 転換期を生きた人々. 德間書店, 1967. p. 153
関ヶ原合戦前後: 封建社会における人間の研究. 德間書店, 1956. p. 129
Turnbull (2011, pp. 63–64)
Kōya Nakamura↗, 徳川家康文書の研究・中巻. 東京: 日本学術振興会, 1959. p. 698
"「どうする家康」徳川家康の秀忠への怒りを解かせた、徳川四天王・榊原康政の直言"↗. sengoku-his.com. 2023
"Tanabe Castle Profile"↗. jcastle.info
国史叢書. National History Research Society, 1916. p. 48
Japanese War History: The Battle of Sekihara. 元真社, 1911
Edmond Papinot. Dictionnaire d'histoire et de géographie du Japon: illustré de 300 gravures, du plusieurs cartes, et suivi de 18 appendices. Libriarie Sansaisha, 1906. p. 2
関ヶ原合戦史料集. 新人物往来社, 1979. p. 421
Shimomura Isao (下村効). "豊臣氏官位制度の成立と発展－公家成・諸大夫成・豊臣授姓－". 日本史研究. 1994, no. 377, pp. 1–26
Kyota Shimomura (下村効). "豊臣氏官位制度の成立と発展－公家成・諸大夫成・豊臣授姓－". 日本史研究. 1994, no. 377
"石田三成の領地は井伊直政へ…関ヶ原合戦に勝ち680万石以上の所領配分権を手にした家康がしたこと"↗. President Online（プレジデントオンライン）. President Inc.. 2023. p. 1–4
"関ヶ原合戦後、徳川家康が東軍諸将を大幅に加増し、厚遇した当たり前の理由"↗. yahoo.co.jp/expert/articles/. 渡邊大門 無断転載を禁じます。 © LY Corporation. 2023
A. L. Sadler↗. Japanese Tea Ceremony: Cha-No-Yu. Tuttle Publishing, 2011. ISBN 978-1-4629-0359-7
"朝日日本歴史人物事典「藤堂高虎」の解説"↗. kotobank
戦国人名事典. 新人物往来社, 1990. p. 698
Masaatsu Hotta↗, 寛政重脩諸家譜 第2輯. Tokyo: 栄進舎出版部, 1923. p. 198
Histoire du Japon : des origines à la fin de l'époque Meiji: Matériaux pour l'étude de la langue et de la civilisation japonaises. FeniXX, 1996. p. 295. ISBN 2402383968
Watanabe Daimon. 関ヶ原合戦人名辞典. 東京: 東京堂出版, 2021. p. 367
Kazuhiko Kasaya↗, 論争 関ヶ原合戦. Shincho Sensho (新潮選書), 2022-09-25. p. 230
Mitsunari Junji↗, "幸鶴期の毛利輝元 : 発給文書と側近衆 (特集 畿内・中国地方の戦国史)". 十六世紀史論叢. 2016, vol. 6, pp. 275, 272, 258. ISSN 2187-8609 naid: 40020817300, ncid: AA12621725
Kenichi Futaki↗, 関ケ原合戦―戦国のいちばん長い日―. Tokyo: Chūōkōron-sha, 1982. p. 200
Kimihito Tsuchiyama. "竹中重門". 別冊歴史読本. 2008, vol. 33, no. 23
15. Sakakibara Yasumasa. 武家事紀. Tokyo: 山鹿素行先生全集刊行会, 1918
館林市史編さん委員会. 館林市史 通史編2 近世館林の歴史. 館林市, 2016
(Chiba-ken) Ōtaki-cho. Ōtaki-cho shi (大多喜町史). Ōtaki-cho, 1991. p. 479
"Reviewed Work: Politics in The Tokugawa Bakufu, 1600–1843 by Conrad D. Totman". Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies. 1968, vol. 28, pp. 216–217. JSTOR 2718602
国史研究会, ed. 關原軍記大成. 国史研究会, 1916. p. 426–427
Tokutomi Sohō. 家康時代 上巻 関原役. 民友社, 1935. p. 244–245
Togawa Yasuie↗, 第9 木下. 三百諸侯. 博文館, 1895. p. 71–74
Watanabe Daimon. "関ヶ原合戦。宮部長房は東軍に与しながら、なぜ戦後は改易されたのか？"↗. Yahoo!ニュース. 2025-05-08
Japanese daily life from the stone age to the present. Carlton Press, 1976. p. 162. ISBN 9780806204710
Vaporis (2019, p. 79)
Vaporis (2019, p. 370)
John Whitney Hall and Marius B. Jansen. Studies in the Institutional History of Early Modern Japan. Princeton University Press, 2015-03-08. p. 117–118. ISBN 978-1-4008-6895-7
Nakai Hitoshi. 近江佐和山城・彦根城. サンライズ出版, 2007. ISBN 978-4-883-25282-4
"三成の佐和山城、徹底破壊 政権交代を見せしめ". 2016
"痕跡一掃、居城「見せしめ」破壊…発掘で裏付け". 2016
林千寿. "慶長五年の戦争と戦後領国体制の創出－九州地域を素材として―". 日本歴史. 2010, no. 742号
"関ヶ原古戦場"↗. Agency for Cultural Affairs↗
Michael Hoffman. "A man in the soul of Japan"↗. Japan Times. 2006-09-10
Glenn and Chris. "Sekigahara"↗. Metropolis Japan. 2017-02-23 }
Masahiko Naiji. "メッケル少佐が関ヶ原合戦を「西軍の勝ち」と言ったことが嘘である3つの理由 近代戦術家は関ヶ原の西軍勝利を確信したか？（前編）"↗. JBpress. 2022-09-13
Shiramine Jun. "メッケル少佐の関ヶ原視察とメッケル伝説 : 司馬遼太郎氏の発言を検証する". 史学論叢 (Shigaku Ronsō) (Journal of Historical Studies). 2022-12-14, vol. 52, pp. 107–109, 111
Kasaya Kazuhiko. "豊臣七将の石田三成襲撃事件―歴史認識形成のメカニズムとその陥穽―". 日本研究. 2000, no. 22集
歴代文化皇國史大觀. Japan: Oriental Cultural Association, 1934. p. 592
Mizuno Goki. "前田利家の死と石田三成襲撃事件". 政治経済史学. 2013, no. 557号, pp. 1–27
Mizuno Goki. 石田三成襲撃事件の真相とは. 戦国史の俗説を覆す. 柏書房, 2016
""Ishida Mitsunari Attack Incident" No attack occurred? What happened to the seven warlords who planned it, and Ieyasu?"↗. rekishikaido. PHP Online. 2023. p. 1–2
Kasaya Kazuhiko. "徳川家康の人情と決断―三成"隠匿"の顚末とその意義―". 大日光. 2000, no. 70号
"七将に襲撃された石田三成が徳川家康に助けを求めたというのは誤りだった"↗. yahoo.co.jp/expert/articles/. 渡邊大門 無断転載を禁じます。 © LY Corporation
Honda Hiroyuki. "豊臣政権下の筑前". 西南地域史研究. 1996, no. 11
Watanabe Daimon. "小早川秀秋は、石田三成の讒言により筑前・筑後を召し上げられたのか？"↗. yahoo.co.jp/expert/articles/. 渡邊大門 無断転載を禁じます。 © LY Corporation. 2023
Honda Hiroyuki 本多博之. "豊臣政権下の筑前". 西南地域史研究 (Studies in the History of the Southwestern Region). 1996, no. 11
Watanabe Daimon. "石田三成は諸大名から蛇蝎のごとく嫌われた、歪んだ人格の持ち主だったのか？"↗. news.yahoo.co.jp/expert/. 渡邊大門 無断転載を禁じます。 © LY Corporation. 2025
Moriaki Hanagasaki. 大谷刑部のすべて. 新人物往来社, 2000. p. 116–118. ISBN 4404028571
"そこで間違えなければ､徳川家康を討てたかもしれない…関ヶ原の戦いで惨敗した石田三成の｢歴史的な判断ミス｣"↗. President Online（プレジデントオンライン）. President Inc.. 2025. p. 1–4
"私は間違ったことはしていない…石田三成が関ヶ原の戦いまでに多くの武将に見捨てられた根本原因"↗. President Online（プレジデントオンライン）. President Inc.. 2023. p. 1–4
"家康が天下を取ったタイミングは関ヶ原合戦ではない…東大教授が語る｢本当の天下分け目の最重要局面｣"↗. President Online（プレジデントオンライン）. President Inc.. 2023. p. 1–4
筑後将士軍談. p. 590–593
"Shogun: The facts behind the fiction"↗. The Independent↗. 2005-05-05
"Sekigahara: The Unification of Japan"↗. BoardGameGeek
Heather Alexandra. "A Guide To The Real-Life Figures In Nioh"↗. Kotaku↗. 2017-11-09
"本当にテレビドラマ史上に残る、見事な合戦シーンになったと思います。"↗. NHK

Bibliography

Anthony J. Bryant↗. Sekigahara 1600: The final struggle for power. Bloomsbury Publishing, 1995. ISBN 978-1-8553-2395-7
Watanabe Daimon. 関ヶ原合戦人名辞典. 東京: 東京堂出版, 2021. ISBN 978-4-490-10915-3
Paul K. Davis. Sekigahara, 21 October 1600. 100 decisive battles : from ancient times to the present. New York: Oxford University Press, 1999. ISBN 978-0-19-514366-9 Paul Davis used the following sources to compile the chapter "Sekigahara, 21 October 1600" in 100 Decisive Battles: From Ancient Times to the Present "Sekigahara, 21 October 1600."
William De Lange. Samurai Battles: The Long Road to Unification. Toyo Press, 2020. ISBN 978-94-92722-23-2 in Davis 1999.
Junji Mitsunari. Mōri Terumoto: Saigoku no gi makaseokaru no yoshi sōrō. Kyōto-shi: Mineruva Shobō, 2016. Shohan ed. ISBN 978-4-623-07689-5. OCLC 949847873
Morgan Pitelka. 5: Severed Heads and Salvaged Swords: The Material Culture of War. Spectacular accumulation: material culture, Tokugawa Ieyasu, and samurai sociability. Honolulu: University of Hawaiʻi press, 2016. ISBN 978-0-8248-5157-6
Arthur Lindsay Sadler. The Maker of Modern Japan: The Life of Tokugawa Ieyasu. G. Allen & Unwin, 1937. ISBN 978-0-598-44090-7 in Davis 1999.
George Bailey Sansom. A history of Japan. 2: 1334-1615. Stanford, Calif: Stanford Univ. Press, 1986. ISBN 978-0-8047-0525-7 in Davis 1999.
Stephen R. Turnbull↗. The samurai: a military history. New York: Macmillan, 1977. 1st American ed. ISBN 978-0-02-620540-5 in Davis 1999.
Stephen R. Turnbull↗. Samurai: The World of the Warrior. Bloomsbury Publishing, 2011. ISBN 978-1-84908-996-8
Stephen R. Turnbull↗ and Giuseppe Rava. Tokugawa Ieyasu: leadership, strategy, conflict. Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing, 2012. ISBN 978-1-84908-574-8
Constantine Nomikos Vaporis. Samurai: an encyclopedia of Japan's cultured warriors. Santa Barbara, California / Denver, Colorado: ABC-CLIO, 2019. ISBN 978-1-4408-4271-9
William Scott Wilson. The Lone Samurai: The Life of Miyamoto Musashi. Tokyo: Kodansha International, 2004. ISBN 978-4-7700-2942-3

External links

SengokuDaimyo.com The website of samurai author and historian Anthony J. Bryant↗. Bryant is the author of the above-mentioned Sekigahara 1600: The Final Struggle for Power.
Several strategy war games based on the battle: Sekigahara: Unification of Japan